Dean Majul: (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: We're gonna... Dean Majul: The condition is very, very bad case, I think, among the old Arabs, that they get the money of orphans for their own use, to the extent that no money is left for these orphans when they grow up, Dean Majul: and they do not even have inheritance, inheritance rights, because they're not adopted, they're just living in the house. Dr. Khalifa: Okay, the next verse is very important, we're gonna close after we read this verse, and I'd like to make a correction. It says on the top, do not marry pagans. I would make it idol worshippers. Do Not Marry Idol Worshipers And if you look at the footnote, it says, pagans include those who are not Jewish, Christians, or Muslim. Jewish, Christian, and Muslim share the common belief in God, in the Hereafter, the angels, Satan, Heaven, and Hell, and all (unintelligible) So, a pagan, I would correct it idol worshipper. Dr. Khalifa: And Muslim, in the footnote, is the real Muslim who worships God alone. A man: Doesn't pagan mean Christian, idol worshipper? Dr. Khalifa: Well, not necessarily. Well, but this is not what the verse says. The verse says, [2:221]  You shall not marry ... It's really, I, I agonized over this, because the Christians are idol worshippers, the Christians who call Jesus God, are idol worshippers. But we can't marry Christians. This is a very tricky verse. Let us read it first. Okay? 221 says, [2:221]  You shall not marry pagan women unless they believe; a believing woman is better than the pagan, even if you like her. Nor shall you permit your women to marry pagans, unless they believe. A believing man is better than the pagan, even if you like him. They invite to Hell, while GOD invites to Heaven and forgiveness, in accordance with His will. He clarifies the revelations for those who take heed. So, in Sura 5, we are permitted to marry Jews and Christians. But you cannot marry a, a Muslim who does not believe God in stating that the Quran is sufficient, that the Quran is complete and perfect. Because when we receive the Quran where every page says, do not worship idols, and the Quran is complete and perfect, etc., etc., then our responsibility is multiplied. I, I mentioned before the example of God's chosen people, and how they have been suffering when Hitler killed 6 million of them, etc., etc. It's because the responsibility doubles when God chooses you and gives you His message, your responsibility is doubled. So, when God gives you a message that says, this message is complete and perfect, and you say, no, it is not complete, then you have deserved the punishment manifold. And this is why we are allowed to marry Christians or Jews, but not a Muslim who does not believe the Quran is complete and perfect. And you have to believe that when you break this law, you'll suffer a lot. When you break this law and marry an idol worshiper, you'll suffer a lot of pain. It's not worth it. You follow this law, you marry a believer, even if you don't like him or her. So, if you're about to get married, then you ask your fiancé or, to believe. And this will serve two purposes. First, it will be a proof of genuine love. He or she changes for you. Second, then you're guaranteed a happy marriage. So, you make it a condition before marriage. And if the candidate is a Muslim who does not believe that the Quran is complete and perfect, you make it a condition of marriage. And you'll be far better off if you say, no, I'm not going to marry you, to continue to believe that Quran is not complete. Now, if you are lax in this commandment, you will suffer a lot of pain. Dr. Khalifa: And the curse of idol worship will carry on to the same generation. A man: Then, you're saying, they're not supposed, the Muslims are not supposed to marry a person who believes in Hadith, right? Dr. Khalifa: Right. A man: Okay. A man: But you are saying the Muslims can't marry a Christian or Jew. Dr. Khalifa: Right. A man: But those Christians, are those Christians cannot be idol worshippers, right? Dr. Khalifa: Quran is saying... A man: Like, a Christian, that Christian should not be Jesus worshipper. Dr. Khalifa: Well, it didn't say that. It says, even as they are, because they were not subject, they did not receive the Quran, they did not look at it. And there is a possibility that they, they will become believers. But the Muslim already looked at the Quran, and saw with his or her own eyes that the Quran says, this book is complete and fully detailed. And they made a decision to reject that, and not to believe God. And that person already made a stand. And God made a stand against that person that you shall not marry him or her. But the Christian, the Christian didn't go through that test. The Christian who believes Jesus is God, the son of God, (unintelligible) may eventually, and it will be easier for that person to come to the Quran alone, than it is for a person who already looked at the Quran and decided that it's not complete, or decided not to believe. Dr. Khalifa: It's very difficult to change. Dean Majul: May I just say something? Dr. Khalifa: Go ahead. Dean Majul: Although something, the problem may not be all, he's worried about this, because it's a real problem, you know, he's putting. But in actual life, I'm sure there are hundreds of thousands of pretty Egyptian girls, Dean Majul: who don't even know one way or the other. Dr. Khalifa: Yeah, right. So, they're available, don't worry. Okay? Because don't imagine that all of the Muslim women already are worshippers of Hadith. Dean Majul: Some of them don't even know the Quran, nor the Hadith. Dr. Khalifa: Right. These are just Dr. Khalifa: quite open. Dean Majul: Yeah. Dean Majul: Yeah. They are the right one for you, the girl, and they're Christian. Dr. Khalifa: Right. Dr. Khalifa: They're exactly like the Christian (unintelligible) Dean Majul: So, don't worry. A woman: (unintelligible) A man: (unintelligible).  Dr. Khalifa: Ok. A man: (unintelligible) Dean Majul: By the way, when I say Egyptian women, this is close to Turkish women, maybe more Turkish women. Dr. Khalifa: We're gonna close, but are there any questions before we close? Dr. Khalifa: We're gonna have the Fajr, IN SHAA ALLAH, at 6 o'clock in the morning. A man: (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: Idol, idol worshippers, we shouldn't marry idol worshippers and pagans. Dr. Khalifa: But there is an exception in Sura 5. Let's look at it in Sura 5. Dean Majul: Sura 5. Dr. Khalifa: Verse 4, no. Carl: is 17. Dr. Khalifa: Verse 5, Sura 5, Verse 5, page 71, it says, [5:5]  Today, all good things are permitted for you. And the food of those who were given previous scriptures is permitted for you, and your food is permitted for them. Also, you are permitted to marry the chaste Muslim women, as well as the chaste women who are Jews or Christians, provided you pay them their due dowries, and maintain chastity, not committing adultery, nor taking secret lovers. Anyone who rejects faith has nullified his work, and will be a loser in the Hereafter. Dr. Khalifa: So, Jewish and Christian, A man: What's chaste? Dr. Khalifa: Chaste means, (unintelligible) I mean, I don't know, chaste means, they don't run around... Dean Majul: They don't commit illicit sexual activities. A man: Oh. A woman: (unintelligible) A woman: (unintelligible) Carl: They're virgin. I mean, hearing... A man: Huh? Dr. Khalifa: Christian and Jewish at the time of Quran were exactly identical to the Christian and Jewish today. Carl: Virgin. Dr. Khalifa: So, there is an exception there. Even the Christian may be an idol. Dr. Khalifa: You can see the difficulty of translating that verse. Dean Majul: And even verse 17 also, the next page that, the definition of pagans are those who say that Christ, the son of Mary, is God. Dean Majul: Now, I would imagine that the majority of, of Christians (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: Yeah. Dean Majul: I mean, (unintelligible), but it is (unintelligible) or something else. Although, there are many Christians, especially in Italy, Dean Majul: who say that Christ is only Dr. Khalifa: a messenger of God Dean Majul: a prophet there. Dean Majul: However, other Christians don't want them to be called Christians, Dr. Khalifa: Yes. Dean Majul: but then that is  Dean Majul: intramural problems between them. Dr. Khalifa: Okay, we're gonna close and we will see you, IN SHAA ALLAH, 6 o'clock in the morning, Dr. Khalifa: and we have to (unintelligible) Dean Majul: (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: Al-Fãtehah Bism Allah Arrahman Arraheem (1:1) Al hamdu Lillahi Rabbil ‘Alameen (1:2) Arrahman Arraheem (1:3) Maliki Yawm Eddeen (1:4) Eyyaka Na’abudu Wa Eyyaka Nasta’aeen (1:5) Ehdina Al-Serata Al-Mustaqeem (1:6) Serata Al-Lazeena An’amta ‘Alayhim Ghayri Al-Maghdoobi ‘Alayhim Wa Laddaalleen (1:7) Dr. Khalifa: Go home and stay out of the streets tonight. Dr. Khalifa: Our verse is the, the last verse of last week. I wanted to touch on it. (unintelligible) we'll start at 222 Bism Allah Arrahman Arraheem. In the name of GOD, the Gracious, the Merciful. The subtitle here is Menstruation. [2:222]  They ask you about menstruation: say, "It is harmful; you shall avoid intercourse with the women during menstruation until they are clean. Once they are clean, you may have intercourse with them in the manner designated by GOD. GOD loves the repenters, and He loves those who are clean." I think this is the only verse in Quran that deals with menstruation, and it is a step forward. A significant word here that could not be translated to English is the word, [2:222]  ... GOD loves the repenters, ... There are two words in Arabic that designate those who repent, and those who continuously repent. And the word used here is the one that means continuously repent. God loves those who continuously repent. Those who repent are called Ta'ibin (تَّائِبین) in Arabic. But the word used here was Tawwabin (تَّوَّٰبِين), which means they, they always repent. And as we, we've been learning in the last few Khutba, is that you cannot go to Heaven with one sin. You have to be sinless to qualify. It was Adam and Eve who committed one sin, and they were kicked out. And one way of erasing sin is repentance. We have to repent continuously, we have to make it a habit, to the extent that when you toss, toss around in your bed, and you're half asleep, you must train yourself to repent, when you're half conscious. Just as you repent, as you turn in your bed, you say, "Please, God forgive me, I repent to you, and hence I never commit a sin again." You mean it. That's what repentance is. Repentance is you're sorry for anything that you might, anything wrong you might have done. And at the same time, you're pledging that you'll never do it again. So, God loves the repenters. I can't think of any English word. I guess we can use multiple words and say, God loves those who continuously repent. And this is one of the, the efficiency of the Arabic language is, is apparent here. And He loves those who are clean. Dr. Khalifa: Yeah. A woman: (unintelligible) A woman: When you (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: Well, it's, it's a, A woman: Yeah. Dr. Khalifa: it's, Dr. Khalifa: No, it's a different slight "I swear to God, I will, I will meet you at the airport." Then, you don't do it. You have to expiate. You have to fast 3 days or (unintelligible). Dr. Khalifa: But when you pledge not to break God's law again, that's, and it's different. A woman: So,... Dr. Khalifa: There's nobody else involved except you. So, it's between you and God. But when you pledge you're gonna meet somebody at the airport, Dr. Khalifa: and there's somebody depending on you. A woman: So, (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: Involve somebody else. A woman: (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: Like I, like I pledged to donate $100 to the poor if I pass this test. Now the, the poor, even though they are unknown, they're still involved in it. So, you can't break it. Dr. Khalifa: But a pledge not to sin is something that's only you is involved in it. A man: (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: Right, unless you make it an oath, like an affidavit. Dr. Khalifa: It was, it was, there was a swearing, "I swear by God" or something. A woman: (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: There are two, two kinds of expiation, there's the promise, the broken promise or somebody else is involved in this, an oath. They're, They're both swearing. Dr. Khalifa: Yeah. Martha: I was thinking that, cause I know, when I like, when I make the intention to, Martha: to allow, it's like, I was thinking that it was more like the intention behind it. Martha: Also, Dr. Khalifa: Yeah. Martha: you know like, when you say that I, you know, I promise never sin or sin or (unintelligible) whatever (unintelligible), Martha: your intention is not to Dr. Khalifa: Right, oh you mean it. That's right. Martha: (unintelligible) So, Martha: you're not perfect and you're going to but at the time you say it, your intention should be you're never, Martha: never ever going to... Dr. Khalifa: That's right. A man: And you mean it. Martha: And so, can you see that the intention is behind it (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: Yeah, this is what I'm saying, it's not, it's not the type of oath that you break and, and requires expiation. A woman: So, there are two (unintelligible) There's a promise, (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: You make an oath. A woman: (unintelligible) oath (unintelligible) A woman: and to make an oath, you swear (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: Yeah. Dr. Khalifa: It's really, the whole thing is common sense. A woman: (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: Evelyn. Yeah. Dr. Khalifa: When you pledge you will not sin again, now, when you, when you fall in sin, that, that was not the intention. You're, you're supposed to be reminding yourself all the time. "Never again God will I sin against you." If you have a certain weakness, if you have a habit of gossiping against the other people, for example, "I, I'm sorry God. I will never gossip again." So, you keep saying this until you really come to that perfection, as far as gossiping is concerned. If you have a bad habit of lies, you say "never, never again will I lie. Not a single lie again." "Please, God forgive me. I repent. I will never lie again." "Never tell a lie under any circumstances, even if I die for it." You know, these kinds of things. So, and you keep reminding yourself until you reach perfection. Because you'll get rid of a bad habit and you'll get into another bad habit and so forth. And you're cleansing yourself one by one. So, this word is very important in this verse that God loves the Tawwabin (تَّوَّٰبِين), those who continuously repent. And the impression from the verse is I describe it against the will that, to the extent that when you are half conscious tossing in bed asleep, as, as soon as you're half conscious, you say "I repent. Forgive me God for my sins. I repent. I'll never do it again." Just make it a habit. [2:222]  ... GOD loves the repenters, ... Because it, it implies also recognition of God, Zikr, commemoration of God. If we can find an excuse to mention God at every chance we get, then we're in good shape. Dr. Khalifa: Yeah. A woman: (unintelligible) if we think of something else, or if we think to ourselves A woman: that I just don't sin again. Dr. Khalifa: Yeah. A woman: And A woman: (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: Yeah. A woman: But if we think to ourselves, "I'll never do it again" then we really need (unintelligible) and we don't worry about what's gonna happen tomorrow, for example. If we consciously (unintelligible) you know (unintelligible) in the moment that you're living in, try to stay as well as you can (unintelligible), and set yourself low even before that. You know, I think a lot of people sabotage themselves by thinking "well, I'll never be able to do that." You know, "I'll never be (unintelligible)" A woman: (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: Well, it's the bombardment from Christianity that tells us the human being is a sinner, the original sin, the inherited sin, and all this (unintelligible), Dr. Khalifa: it makes us feel that we're sinners, that we're doomed sinners, A woman: hopeless Dr. Khalifa: hopelessly sinners. That's not true. Dr. Khalifa: You don't have to be a sinner. A woman: You should have that hope. (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: You must be ready to meet God any time. If you die now and you go to Heaven, then you have to think about this. Now, we have to think of it. We all drive, we can go drive, and never make it. So, we must be ready. We have to be ready all the time. And if you bear in mind that you cannot go to Heaven with one sin, not a single sin, then actually as a believer in God alone, you have to be determined not to have anything in your record. None. And the way to erase sin is repentance. The sins that you cannot repent are the ones that you know something is wrong and you do it, knowing it is wrong. You can't repent from that. You have to pay for it. You have to pay for it here. That's the only alternative, actually. Because, boy, paying for it over there means eternal Hell. It means misery. There is no such thing as paying over there. We have to pay for it here. So, it will be, will be even (unintelligible) as far as sins are concerned. The rest... Now, this is, this is where the positive actions come in the picture, the Five Prayers a day. They will help erase sins. Fasting of Ramadan, these are positive things that erase the negative things, erase sins also because there are almost surely sins that we're not aware of. You're passed by your brother or sister, and you didn't greet him or her properly. Well, there was something on your mind, and your brother or sister thought you, Dr. Khalifa: you made a face. Dr. Khalifa: Yeah. A man: I read somewhere that the, this, this, the great sins you committed before you seriously became a believer in one God, that these are cause you were unaware, you weren't aware of them, what's so bad when you did it? Well, read the Quran or even if you read it, maybe you had missed that particular verse that, A man: that these are forgiven more, more easily. Dr. Khalifa: Not only forgiven, they are converted into credits. The Quran teaches that when you come to God and you (unintelligible) a, you know, you come to God (unintelligible) a great repentance, and apologize for all the past sins, and you show remorse, and determination never to do it again, they actually become credits. And I remember one time I was flying to Egypt and there was a gentleman next to me. I think it was a major in the army or something in the, in the Egyptian army. And he was collecting all the bottles of liquor, you know, from the people around him and drinking them up. So, I, I couldn't help telling, you know, you are accumulating a good number of sins this way. And he said, are you familiar with the verse in Quran that says, when you repent God converts sins to credits. I said, yeah. He said, well I'm trying to accumulate as many sins as possible, so I can convert them to credits in that way. That was the best excuse I've ever heard. Dr. Khalifa: Yeah. A man: (unintelligible) excuse Dr. Khalifa: I think that was the only verse he ever remembered from Quran. But it is true that if you spend the life of idol worship and sin and so forth, and then you declare a great repentance you come to God then all your sins are converted into credits. I have a feeling that this conversion to credits accompanied by abolishing the process that is quite severe. But when you look, when you look at what it's doing, the cleansing process and the conversion of sins to credits, it is actually a blessing, a great blessing, the blessing in disguise, because everything passes, all hardships pass. But to send it in your record on the Day of Judgment means just unequal misery. The Quran says, Those who barely miss Hell, and enter Heaven have triumphed a great, [3:185]  ... has attained a great triumph. ... So, we must be among the repenters, those who continuously repent. 223, [2:223]  Your women are assets for you. And, you may enjoy your assets however you like, so long as you maintain righteousness. You shall observe GOD, and know that you will ultimately meet Him. Give good news to the believers. So, these are clear. These are, these are the first x-rated verses that we came across since the beginning of the Quran. But the key sentences here are in verse 222, [2:222]  ... in the manner designated by GOD. ... That's a key expression. And in 223, [2:223]  ... so long as you maintain righteousness. ... So, there are limits beyond which there will, there will be abuse or misuse. Dr. Khalifa: Next subtitle... A man: (unintelligible) this one says, it says, [2:223]  Your women are assets ... A man: Is it, does that mean possession or something? Dr. Khalifa: No. A man: (unintelligible) what (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: It means, they add to your life. They add to your life. A man: Now, how does that relate, you know, in the (unintelligible), you know, like this deals, it seems like this deals more so with men A man: rather than with women, I mean. Dr. Khalifa: Well, the... A man: I mean, it doesn't say, it doesn't tell the women, the men are assets for them. Dr. Khalifa: No, we just did that you are their confidence, and they are your confidence. Dr. Khalifa: Where was that verse? A man: That's 223. A man: This... Dr. Khalifa: No, there was a verse that mentioned confidence. No. A woman: It's 187. Dr. Khalifa: 187? Dr. Khalifa: Yeah, 2:187 it says, [2:187]  Permission is granted for you herein; you have intercourse with your spouses during the nights of fasting. They are your confidant, and you are their confidant. ... So, it's a, it's a two-way, it's a two-way street. Not a one-way. But it is a fact of life that men are the ones who are usually demanding. We had to hear Glenda's voice, my goodness, she was so quiet this afternoon. Dr. Khalifa: Ok. Rashid, you wanna, you wanna take the (unintelligible)? Rashid: 224? Dr. Khalifa: 224 and on. Rashid: [2:224]  You shall not... Rashid: [2:225] ... the Forgiver, and the Clement. If he wasn't here, then he wouldn't know what your, what your pledges were in the first place. And if he wasn't on this ship, he wouldn't have the power to forgive them. And I have to (unintelligible) here forgiving and clement, meaning, when a governor gives clemency, it means he gives the pardon. A man is in death row, ready to die for his mortal sins, and his, the governor calls a plea of clemency. He's made, and the governor says, well, he has, he receives clemency, that he'll be pardoned. So, God is the ultimate One who is clement. Much worse than the electric chair requires (unintelligible) So, it's, people talk a lot. And that, you know, I hear people swear a lot for (unintelligible). But it's not a good practice to say, God this, and God that, and God damn this, to use the name of God in vain. Or to use the word of, word, the powerful words of, of, of scripture and of God as a, as a part of idle conversation. A man: Is that recommended here? Dr. Khalifa: Just wanted to think for a moment. A man: I just wanted, it's (unintelligible) way of seeing. A lot of people, they talk about God, and they appear to be righteous in their speech. But really, it's not what you say that it's important. You're held responsible for what you intend to do, or what your motivation is. Here, we have in the Quran, what we know from psychology, the underlying structure of human behavior is motivation. It's what you intend to do, or what you're motivated to do, that makes the difference. So, it's something you can read in modern psychology, which is right here in the Quran, and the person's motives, or their intention, is the true way of deciding what they're all about, and not just what they say. And sometimes, the motives are very deep-lined. The motivation is the, the key to understanding human nature, and the human mind. People can draw a line between this and that to say something is, is, is one thing and another. First of all, they must have a motive. There's a very famous book on mathematics called "The Laws Form" which almost approaches the mystical in its conception of the world in the first sentence, he says, The motive is prior to distinction. Before we draw a boundary between A and B, we have to have a motive. A man: That's, that's right here in the Quran. Dr. Khalifa: (unintelligible) was asking about the expiation for the (unintelligible) about their sins. You will see the verse 225, it says, [2:225] ... He holds you responsible for your actual intentions. ... So, the intention was not to commit a sin, it's the (unintelligible) treated (unintelligible) However, to illustrate the thing, (unintelligible) to help us see the common sense of it, for example, Ahmad said, I pledge, I swear to God, I will not smoke. And then, he came to me one day in the office, and he had the withdrawal, nicotine withdrawal symptoms, and he said, what am I supposed to do to break my oath? And he said, ... And I said, you have to fast three days, or feed ten poor people. He said, can I smoke now? He said, and then, in other words, he decided to either fast three days, or feed, to feed ten poor people. But in the case of saying, I pledge I will never sin again, then the person cannot say, okay, I wanna commit adultery. Let's, let's see, what am I supposed to do? I fast three days, or to feed ten poor people, and then go commit adultery. This would be a premeditated sin, you know, and you can see the nonsense of it. It doesn't make sense. He, he, he decided to feed ten poor people, and he went on smoking. But that's not a sin. The sin that he expiated for was breaking the oath. And you pledge not to commit a sin, you can't say, I'm gonna feed ten poor people, and then go commit a sin. Dr. Khalifa: Yeah. A woman: So, if you mean to do something, you actually need to do it, like, I don't swear (unintelligible). That's why (unintelligible) And you know it (unintelligible) unforgivable A woman: I mean, if you (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: Anything is forgivable, but idol worship. A woman: I know but you're talking about (unintelligible) A woman: You know (unintelligible) you can't say, okay, I... Dr. Khalifa: No, you can't defend from premeditated sin. You have to pay for it. A woman: Premeditated? Dr. Khalifa: Right. But anything is forgivable, except idol worship. We have to, we have to make distinction between forgivability and, and repentance, and, and paying for. Repentance, Forgivability, anything is forgivable, except idol worship. Do you remember one Khutba (unintelligible) he said, some people when we tell them that you don't follow Hadith and Sunnah because they are from Satan, they accuse you of disrespecting the prophet. So, the other choice is idol worship. They, tell them, which choice is a sin, idol worship or disrespecting the prophet? The Quran states clearly that anything, everything is forgivable but not idol worship. So, you want to choose something that's forgivable. So,... But they, these ar.  the only choices. I would easily take disrespect to the prophet. That's the other, the only choice. But, of course, we respect the prophet. God chose him to have him utter the last scripture out of his mouth. And the people who really love Jesus are the ones who know him as he really is. Dr. Khalifa: The people who love Muhammad are the ones who follow him as he really wants to be followed. A man: (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: Anything is forgivable but idol worship. Now, if you talk about a person who dies as a hypocrite who says he's a believer, but he's not a believer, Dr. Khalifa: well, that's unforgivable, when he's not a believer to start with. A man: Doesn't the Quran tell you about the hypocrites? Doesn't it say that at one time they were believers and then they're lost? A man: Maybe, their history is on hypocrites. Dr. Khalifa: No, but they can repent from this and they become believers. They can become believers. A person can be an idol worshiper and become a believer. Dr. Khalifa: Prophet Muhammad himself was an idol worshiper and he became a believer. He was guided. A man: But I'm like, you know, (unintelligible) that says the hypocrites can't be believers or forgiven. Dr. Khalifa: If they die, die, die in a state of hypocrisy, or die in a state of disbelief, Dr. Khalifa: or a state of idol worship, A man: Salãmun ‘Alaykum. Dr. Khalifa: ‘Alaykum Al-Salãm Dr. Khalifa: they cannot be forgiven. I mean, first of all, the hypocrites and the disbelievers give up their right to be forgiven anyway. Dr. Khalifa: Because they don't recognize God. A man: Well, it says here when, when, [63:5]  When they are told, "Come let the messenger of Allah ask for your forgiveness," they turn their heads, the way they are forced by their arrogance. A man: [63:6]  Whether you ask forgiveness for them, or do not ask forgiveness for them; Allah will not forgive them. Allah does not guide the wicked people. Dr. Khalifa: We're talking about believers who... Because the majority of believers have fallen in idol worship. And almost 100% of the believers go through a stage of idol worship. And then, they get through that. So, first the disbelievers, they are, I mean, these are out, naturally. And the hypocrites are actually disbelievers, except they are worse. Because they are among the believers. Dr. Khalifa: But they don't believe. A man: It's not the degree of disbelief. Dr. Khalifa: Right. It's a worse degree. If a disbeliever, you know, he's a disbeliever and you're alert, and you, you talk to him on that basis. But when a person comes to you with the Quran under his arm and later tells you, "I don't believe that this is complete" and he's righteous and then he gets up to try the Noon with you, then he says "this is, this is not complete." God says this is complete, and he says this is not complete. That's a hypocrite. And he's worse because he appears to be righteous, and you think he's a great Muslim, and you listen. Usually they're very eloquent. Dr. Khalifa: That's the worst, that's the worst kind. A man: I had a question. (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: The Quran says, they will be in [4:145]  ... the lowest pit of Hell, ... because of that. Now, if, if a person says I'm a disbeliever, you will, you will listen to him or her knowing that they just have to be a disbeliever. If the person comes to you as a great believer and then takes you away from the path, Dr. Khalifa: it's a lot worse. A man: Quran says worthy of one time, I mean, hypocrites were people who believed at one time, and then they, Dr. Khalifa: Well, not necessarily. A man: and then they... Dr. Khalifa: It could be the other way around. In fact, many of them became believers. Dr. Khalifa: (unintelligible) A man: A person, you know, who'd like to be a Muslim (unintelligible) some time the other followers of Quran. let's say that Quran says, don't drink alcohol, don't (unintelligible) unintentionally or intentionally (unintelligible) A man: it's a little bit sin, right? Dr. Khalifa: He's a sinner. A man: (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: No. A man: Because he's not following the guidance. Dr. Khalifa: That's right. Yeah, he's a sinner. Dr. Khalifa: But if he sits somewhere and said, I don't drink, you know, then that's hypocrisy. A man: (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: Yeah. A man: Well, I had something about Muhammad, that's a little bit off. Dr. Khalifa: Is (unintelligible) here? For example, when (unintelligible) and said, I am Muslim, I Pray, but I drink. Now, he's not (unintelligible), but he's sinner. Cause he's making a scene. Dr. Khalifa: And a lot of us do that. A man: Just as, just because, we had, we had, we had two people here from Seattle who are gonna go back and hear this. I just heard this recently about Muhammad, we should... It's a justification for Sunni Wahabi Ok, and, and I've, I've heard you explain it before, but they're gonna have the same thing thrown at them, I know it. Ok. It's the idea that Muhammad was a good model. Ok. It's like, he, he got the Quran, and, you know, he follows it. And, and let's look at his life, and let's, let's model our life after his life. This is a justification for Sunnah, Ok. And the thing that he did, Ok, because he's the prophet, so he's a good model, so let's follow his model. A man: Well, that's, that's...  Dr. Khalifa: This is what they say? A man: Well, that's... Dr. Khalifa: The Quran says, don't follow his model. The Quran says, he gave attention to the rich man and neglected the poor man because he's poor, and gave his attention to the rich man because he's rich. The Quran says don't do that. The Quran says the prophet feared the people instead of fearing God. And the Quran says don't do that. Dr. Khalifa: Therefore, this claim is unvalid, invalid. A man: Before (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: In other words, the Quran says, do not follow the example of the prophet. A man: Avoid that (unintelligible) common things they say... Dr. Khalifa: Oh, they're fully aware. Yeah, they know that there... Yep. A man: It says that, (unintelligible) for up and doing a sin Dr. Khalifa: is idol worship. A man: is idol worship. A man: I wanna ask you a follow-up. I don't know (unintelligible), but I know this, this, this it says, (unintelligible) the Muslims. No one (unintelligible) A man: (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: Okay. Well, if you look at the verse carefully, it will, it will mean that this person is a disbeliever. It's in Sura 4. Dr. Khalifa: (unintelligible) what the verse says, A man: (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: I know that's a good, that's a very good question. A man: (unintelligible) A woman: 95 is (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: Ok. 92 says the grossness of murder. There is no believer... [4:92]  No believer kills another believer, except by mistake. Whoever kills a believer by mistake shall expiate by freeing ... Okay. (unintelligible) is 93. 93 says, [4:93]  As for the one who kills a believer deliberately, his retribution is Hell, wherein he abides forever, and GOD is angry with him, curses him, and has prepared for him a terrible retribution. Because it's a, it's a gross, he could not be a believer. He killed a believer deliberately. You know, you notice in 92, it says, [4:92]  No believer kills another believer, except by mistake. ... But in 93, it doesn't say, as for the believer who kills a believer on purpose. It says, it says, Dr. Khalifa: [4:93]  As for the one who kills a believer deliberately, ... A man: Yes. Dr. Khalifa: He was this executing him as a believer. And you notice how to also (unintelligible) by saying, [4:93]  ... his retribution is Hell, ... As if that is not enough, it says, [4:93]  ... wherein he abides forever, and GOD is angry with him, ... which is worse than Hell. [4:93]  ... curses him, ... which is even worse. Dr. Khalifa: [4:93]  ... and has prepared for him a terrible retribution. A man: That's (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: It's like saying, if he slaps you in the face, I'm gonna carry you up, and throw you on the ground, Dr. Khalifa: and then step on you, and count you to death, and then whip you a hundred lashes. A man: That's (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: All right. But I want you to notice the word of the Quran. In 92, it says, [4:92]  No believer kills another believer, except by mistake. ... And in 93, it says, [4:93]  As for the one who kills a believer deliberately, ... It says, that person is not a believer, but (unintelligible) a believer. A true believer, who reads the Quran, realizes that killing one person is like killing the, the whole humanity. But as far as the person who was killed, that's the end of the world. Dr. Khalifa: Yeah. A man: I'm (unintelligible).  As far as belief is concerned, (unintelligible) people (unintelligible) us in our belief. And a lot of us might perceive ourselves to be believing, cause when this, the, the situation of a test arises, we might turn back. A man: You know, what I'm saying, in that case, we would become (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: Right. A man: We would become hypocrites. Dr. Khalifa: Right. A man: The only way that we could really know our faith is through a test. And, like, you know, again, when I was reading the word of the Sura itself, A man: it says here, it says,... Dr. Khalifa: But, see, if they're guiding us to hypocrisy, then we, we end up in the lowest pit of Hell. We have people in this city who are studying the Quran Dr. Khalifa: and pretend to be very religious, and they go around trying to keep the people away from the Quran. A man: But it's only through a test that we really know how righteous we are. A man: Look, none of us really know where we're coming from. A man: Allah Subhanahu Wa Ta'ala made us, made us Muslims. Dr. Khalifa: Actually this is... Dr. Khalifa: Actually this is, but I wanted to say in Sura 8, A man: (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: we have verses that, that the hypocrites can stop being hypocrites, and they can come and join the believers. A man: (unintelligible) Dr. Khalifa: People can repent from idol worship, hypocrisy, disbelief. It's the time of death that determines, that determines what the person really is. Now, if you die as a, in a state of hypocrisy, (unintelligible) So, if we're talking about the, at the time of death... Dr. Khalifa: But people in their life can go to hypocrisy just...